Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2011; 2.5 linear feet (2 full letter document boxes, 1 half letter document box, 2 medium card boxes); 43 Gigabytes (83 digital video and text files)
  - Jan Everhart interviewed by Anna Holley, 2011 March 19; Everhart, Jan; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Jan Everhart shares her experiences as an ordained Methodist pastor living in Iowa. She discusses her political thoughts surrounding gay marriage, and details her 22 ½ year relationship with her partner, Jan Ratliff. Everhart also discusses queerness within the United Methodist Church, her dedication to the church's values, and her radical perceptions of the Bible. Finally, she sheds light on her "quiet" activism, commitment to service learning, and passion for mentoring young adults.
    Everhart, Jan
    - Video interview of Jan Everhart
    - Transcript of interview of Jan Everhart (Box 1)
  - Lori Harris interviewed by Lalitha Muthusamy, 2011 April 18; Harris, Lori; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Lori Harris (b. 1957) was born in Dayton, Ohio, and was raised primarily by her mother and her maternal grandparents. Her mother worked in her grandmother's beauty salon and later became an administrative assistant at a local high school. Harris identifies as African American and part Blackfoot and as gay/lesbian. She was raised as a Baptist, later became a Methodist, and currently has no religious affiliation, but still considers herself a spiritual person. In the 1980's and 90's, she was involved with an organization called "The Black Lesbian Support Group."
    She attended a vocational high school school, and later went on to take courses in Communication at Trinity University from 2006-2007. Harris worked as a legal assistant and secretary for a law firm from 1975 to 2007, when she decided to attend Smith College as an Ada Comstock Scholar. While at Smith, Harris worked as a Junior Curator/Public Historian at the Smithsonian Institution, had an archival internship at the Black Women's Health Imperative, and was a Kahn Liberal Arts Student Fellow during the 2009-2010 academic year. During the 2010-2011 academic year, she worked as an OCIP/CDO Intern at the Sophia Smith Collection.
    In 2011, Harris received her BA in American Studies, with a concentration in museum studies and archival studies.
    In this oral history, Lori Harris describes her childhood growing up in Dayton, Ohio with her siblings and her experiences dealing with her mother's divorces and her abusive stepfather. The interview focuses on her journey as a working adult returning to college to receive her bachelor's degree in American Studies. She talks at length about her academic and scholarly work in black women and lesbian health issues, as well as her experiences in the academy as a non-traditional aged student scholar of color. Harris' story about her time in Washington, D.C. as a volunteer with the Black Lesbian Support Group also sheds light on the internal race dynamics of LGBT organizations during the 1970's and 1980's. Her story adds a new perspective on the LGBT movements that gained momentum before and during the AIDS epidemic and, in particular, the voice of the marginalized, tokenized black lesbians, that has been scarcely heard before. It also delves into Harris' personal life, and her journey in discovering herself through romantic and familial relationships.
    Harris, Lori
    - Video interview of Lori Harris
    - Transcript of interview of Lori Harris (Box 1)
  - Patricia Holland (pseudonym) interviewed by Sarah Bastress, 2011 April 22; Howland, Pam; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Patricia Holland (b. 1949) was born in Syracuse, New York, but grew up with her family in California and Virginia, and lived in New Jersey for one year. Her father was a landscape architect for the National Park Service and on the faculty of the University of Virginia. Holland's mother stayed at home until Patricia and her siblings began to attend school, then became the assistant to the Principal for Instruction at Mclean High School, and eventually became a guide at Monticello where she worked for 25 years. Holland has a brother who is 66, and three sisters who are 58, 55, and 53. Holland attended the Virginia Commonwealth University, where she began her long dedication to community organizing, helping to develop the Welfare Rights Organization in Richmond, Virginia. She graduated in 1971with a BA in Social Welfare. Since her first job volunteering for VISTA and organizing a public housing tenant union, Holland has committed to fighting for welfare rights and self-help housing. In 1977, she became the Coordinator for Children's Services for the Pittsfield, Massachusetts Department of Mental Health's Division of Drug Rehabilitation. In 1982, Holland became the Program Manager for Project Aim, Incentive Community Enterprises, Inc. in Springfield, Massachusetts, where she developed and managed community homes for formerly institutionalized people. In the late 1970s, she purchased a sheep farm in Massachusetts, which she lived and worked on congruently with her welfare work until the early 1990s. Holland attended the Center for Public Policy and Administration at the University of Massachusetts and received her Masters in Public Administration in 1987. After working in housing projects for over two decades, Holland has become passionate about building affordable sustainable housing, and helping other women to do the same. Recently, she helped found the Westfield Energy Efficiency Trades Center (WEETC), a non-profit facility for women-owned businesses to build a healthier environment and economy, of which she also serves as the Executive Director. Holland serves on many local committees involving social welfare and sustainability.
    In this oral history, Patricia Holland describes aspects of herself as a child that are still relevant and important to her identity today, many stemming from her experiences of being a young girl living on a farm. The interview centers on her struggle to accept and celebrate herself as a woman and a lesbian, as well as the relationships that both prevented and allowed her to do so. She discusses her dedication to anti-poverty work and self-help housing, and why self-help housing is the tangible way of making a difference, especially for women.
    Howland, Pam
    - Video interview of Patricia Holland
    - Transcript of interview of Patricia Holland (Box 2)
  - Annie Rachele Lanzillotto interviewed by Caitlin Dubois, 2011 April 3; Lanzillotto, Annie; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Annie Rachele Lanzillotto (b. 1963) was born in the Bronx, New York, to Italian-American parents. Her father, Joseph Lanzillotto, was an iceman and later an electrician, and served in World War II. Lanzillotto's mother, Rachele Lanzillotto, graduated from Jane Addams High School in the Bronx with training in cosmetology. She became a hairdresser and manicurist after divorcing Annie's father in 1975. She is the youngest of four children (Charles, 1948; Rosemarie, 1950; John, 1952). In 1975, at the age of twelve, Annie and her mother moved to Yonkers. In 1986, Lanzillotto graduated with an Honors BA in Medical Anthropology from Brown University. While at Brown, Lanzillotto worked various service jobs. In 1985, she attended the American University of Cairo where she did her thesis work at the Egyptian Ministry of Health, where she first began to "play with gender" by sometimes dressing as a man. In 1990, she went on to get her MFA in writing from Sarah Lawrence University. At age 18, Lanzillotto was diagnosed with Hodgkin's Lymphoma, and, due to the radiation, she was later diagnosed with Thyroid Cancer at age 35. Today, Lanzillotto identifies herself as a "theatre teacher, writing instructor, song writer, performer poet, director of solo theatre, director of site specific theatre, memoirist, rock vocalist, and community organizer." In 1993, she entered the theatre world by writing and performing Confessions of a Bronx Tomboy. Theatrical highlights include her public art installation and performance A Stickball Memoir, curated by City Lore for the 2001 Smithsonian Folk Life Festival; her play Pocketing Garlic, commissioned by Franklin Furnace in 1994; her one woman show, How To Wake Up a Marine in a Foxhole, which premiered at The Kitchen Solo Voice's Series in 1998, and her two year site-specific work entitled, a'Schapett! (the act of wiping your plate clean with the heel of the bread, and savoring the juices) at The Arthur Avenue Retail Market in the Bronx. In 2010, The Annie Lanzillotto Band came out with a rock album entitled, "Blue Pill."
    Lanzillotto is currently a member of the Italian American Writers Association, the Italian American Historical Association, the Franklin Furnace Archive (which preserves and encourages avant-garde art by underrepresented communities in Brooklyn), Dixon Place, and The Kitchen. She was also a member of Act Up: Rank and File from 1986-1988, and is presently a member of the Remember the Triangle Fire Coalition Executive Committee.
    In this oral history, Annie Lanzillotto describes her childhood in a working class Italian American family, with focused attention on the transition that moved the narrator and her mother from the Bronx to Yonkers, New York in 1974. The interview also explores the impact of her father's domestic violence on her family. Lanzillotto also discusses gender identity and the messages she received regarding sexuality and gender while attending Catholic schools, Brown University, and the American University in Cairo. In addition, Lanzillotto describes the impact of being diagnosed with Hodgkin's Lymphoma at age 18 and Thyroid Cancer at age 35, along with her understandings of work and development of an "artist family." Lanzillotto also characterizes her participation in the Triangle Factory Fire Remembrance held on March 25, 2011.
    Lanzillotto, Annie
    - Video interview of Annie Rachele Lanzillotto
    - Transcript of interview of Annie Rachele Lanzillotto (Box 2)
  - Betty Morningstar interviewed by Jeni Turner, 2011 April 8; Morningstar, Betty; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Betty Morningstar (b. 1952) grew up in Brookline, Massachusetts. In 1971, she graduated from Smith College with an A.B. in Psychology. She pursued her graduate studies at Smith, earning her M.S.W. in 1977 and her Ph.D. in 1989. In addition to her extensive studies at Smith, Betty holds a M.A. from the Andover Newton Theological School. Since 1983, she has worked as a therapist in a private practice. Her teaching experience includes the Schools for Social Work at Smith and Simmons Colleges. Currently, she serves as the president of the Massachusetts Chapter of National Association of Social Workers (NASW), and in the past, has served as the chair of the national LGBT committee of NASW. She is also the former chair of the Social Workers for Peace and Justice. Additionally, she contributed to the book Lesbians and Lesbian Families: Multiple Reflections with the chapter Lesbian Parents: Understanding Developmental Pathways, (1999).
    In this oral history, Betty Morningstar describes her evolving relationship with her parents, including their attendance at her commitment ceremony. She explains her schooling experiences as a Jewish student at both private and public schools, and articulates how many choices in her earlier adulthood manifested from her lack of choices within the social times growing up. Her educational and ideological explorations during her studies at Smith College, as both and undergraduate and graduate student, highlight her positioning on the cusp of major political movements of the late 1960s and 1970s. Additionally, she chronicles her emerging feminist and lesbian ideologies during her personal growth of relationships and professional development. From a realization in her early childhood to become a therapist to being the president of the Massachusetts chapter of the National Association of Social Workers, Betty has demonstrated a clear professional trajectory. The interview includes experiences as a single, lesbian woman searching for the means to create a family with children and a supportive partner. All the while, Betty fuses the clinical practice of therapy with the exploration of the religious, personal self. Betty's story details the avenues she explored to become a lifelong learner, an active community member, and a lesbian parent and spouse.
    Morningstar, Betty
    - Video interview of Betty Morningstar
    - Transcript of interview of Betty Morningstar (Box 2)
  - Carole Oglesby interviewed by Zeina Dajani, 2011 February 24; Oglesby, Carole A.; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Carole Oglesby (b. 1938) grew up in Oklahoma and California. She earned her BA and MS from the University of California, Los Angeles in 1961 and 1964 respectively, and earned her PhD in Physical Education from Purdue University in 1969. She also earned a PhD in Counseling at Temple University in 1999. Oglesby started her career as a professional softball player, competing in national level softball championships in 1962, 63, and 65, and coached teams from both Purdue University and the University of Massachusetts. Oglesby is a professor emeritus in sport psychology (2001) from Temple University and was Chairperson in Kinesiology at California State University Northridge from 2003 to 2009.
    As a sports psychology consultant, she has worked with Olympians and Pan American Games champions in rowing, cycling, para-Olympic cycling, and with the USA Deaf Women's VB team. Oglesby was on the executive committee of the USA World University Games group from 1972-1992, the US Olympic Committee House of Delegates from 1992-1996, and sat on the USOC Sport Psychology Registry for 12 years. She has presented papers and conducted training and leadership workshops in 31 countries. She has also published several pioneering works, including, Women and Sport: Myth to Reality (1978); Black Women and Sport (co-edited, 1978); and Encyclopedia of Women and Sport in America (1998). She is past-president of WomenSport International, served on the Executive Committee of the International Working Group for Women and Sport, and was the principal contributor to the UN-DAW monograph, Women 2000 and Beyond: Women, Gender, Equality and Sport, 2009. She is a recipient of the Women's Sports Foundation Billie Jean King award, AAHPERD R. Tait McKinzie award, ICSSPE Phillip Noel Baker Research award.
    In this oral history, Carole Oglesby describes her childhood with her feminist mother and supportive father. The interview is a quick overview of her relationships, activism, political activity, and family life. Oglesby details her introduction to feminism, and credits her interest in sport psychology as stemming from her life long battle to attain equal rights for women in sports. She has worked on many different projects, for example she talks about her work with the 1977 Women's Conference in Huston, and her work with Title IX.
    Oglesby, Carole A.
    - Video interview of Carole Oglesby
    - Transcript of interview of Carole Oglesby (Box 2)
  - Cody Penotte interviewed by Grace Martin, 2011 April 23; Penotte, Cody; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Cody Penotte (b. 1957) grew up in Ohio and Florida, living with two foster families after leaving her family of origin at the age of twelve. After attending high school, she spent a year in a cultural anthropology program, during which she lived in Mexico, Canada, and the Sea Islands. After this, she spent two years as an apprentice to a Shaker furniture maker, and, since then, she has been a passionate furniture maker. Penotte is currently an Ada Comstock Scholar at Smith College, majoring in Education. She lives on Nantucket with her partner of thirty years.
    In this oral history, Cody Penotte describes her very diverse childhood in several different families and socioeconomic backgrounds, her equally diverse job experience, and the factors that led her to pursue a Bachelor's degree at Smith College. The interview focuses on the numerous jobs she has held, particularly in the field of woodworking, as well as her experience with the Ada Comstock program, and her relationship with her current partner. Penotte's story also details the ways in which diversity in her upbringing has influenced her life.
    Penotte, Cody
    - Video interview of Cody Penotte
    - Transcript of interview of Cody Penotte (Box 2)
  - Catherine Pittman interviewed by Elizabeth (Bethy) Williams, 2011 March 12; Pittman, Catherine; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Catherine Pittman was born in Flint, Michigan on August 3, 1961. She is a graduate of Central Michigan University and Northern Illinois University (where she received her Ph.D. in Clinical Psychology). She has taught at Saint Mary's College in Notre Dame, Indiana since 1989. Though she is a practicing clinical psychologist, Pittman's passion has always been for teaching. At Saint Mary's, she has served as advisor for several campus organizations that raise awareness of issues such as violence against women and LGBTQ visibility. She also co-authored a book with Elizabeth (Lisa) Karle entitled Extinguishing Anxiety: Whole Brain Strategies to Relieve Fear and Stress.
    Catherine Pittman currently lives with her two daughters Melinda and Arrianna in South Bend, Indiana, where she is a community activist in the debate of whether to amend the city's Human Rights Ordinance to include sexual orientation and gender identity. She served as spokesperson for South Bend Equality, a group advocating for the Human Rights Amendment, from 2006 until 2011.
    In this interview, Catherine Pittman discusses growing up in Owosso, Michigan as the oldest of 10 children raised in a single parent household. She recounts her religious and spiritual journey—growing up with Catholicism and later finding a home in Unitarian Universalism and earth-centered spiritualities. Pittman talks of her academic passions in the field of psychology as well as her activism as a professor at Saint Mary's College, a small Catholic women's college in Notre Dame, Indiana. On a personal level, she discusses her divorce with her husband, her relationship with her two daughters, and her identity as a bisexual woman. Explaining her current activist work, Pittman discusses her efforts to amend the South Bend, Indiana Human Rights Ordinance to include gender identity and sexual orientation.
    Pittman, Catherine
    - Video interview of Catherine Pittman
    - Transcript of interview of Catherine Pittman (Box 2)
  - Bet Power interviewed by Rhys McGovern, 2011 April 11; Power, Bet; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Bet Power (b. 1950) is an FTM transgender man who has chosen not to medically transition. He is a longtime activist and agitator for LGBT rights. Power was raised in Chicago, and has been a resident of the Northampton area since the late 1970s. He identified as a stone butch, and lived and socialized in the lesbian community in Chicago and Northampton during the 1970s and early 1980s, and has identified as an FTM transgender man since 1983. Since the late 1970s, Power has been curator of the Sexual Minority archives, which document the lives and histories of varied sexual minorities, including lesbians, bisexuals, gay men, transgendered people, S/M leatherfolk, and fetishists. He founded the East Coast FTM group in 1992 and continues to host the monthly meetings in his home.
    In this oral history, Bet Power describes his childhood in a working-class family in Chicago, and his experiences in the Polish Roman Catholic community as a child. The interview focuses on his involvement and experiences with the lesbian feminist movement in Chicago and Northampton in the 1970s and 1980s, his experiences coming out as a transman in Northampton in the early 1980s, his activism within the LGBTQ community, and the history and development of the Sexual Minorities Archive.
    Power, Bet
    - Video interview of Bet Power
    - Transcript of interview of Bet Power (Box 2)
  - Ellen Shumsky interviewed by Dara Kagan, 2011 March 14; Shumsky, Ellen; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Ellen Shumsky (b. 1941) grew up in Brooklyn, received her B.S. from Brooklyn College in l96l, and earned her Masters in library science from the Pratt Institute in l964. Shumsky taught high school science in the New York City school system for four years, followed by ten years as a school librarian. In the late 1960s, Shumsky studied photography in France with her mentor and brother-in-law Harold Chapman. She returned to the United States in 1969 to join the Gay Liberation Front (GLF). Shumsky co-founded the Radicalesbians and co-authored the lesbian feminist text "The Woman-Identified Woman" under the name of Ellen Bedoz. She served as the principle photographer for GLF's newspaper Come Out. In 1979, Schumsky received her Masters in social work from SUNY Stony Brook. From 1980 to the present, she has worked as a psychiatric social worker, a psychotherapist in private practice, and teacher and supervisor at psychotherapy and psychology institutes in New York City.
    In this oral history, Ellen Shumsky describes growing up in a Jewish community in Brooklyn and her experiences learning about photography in France in the 1960s. The interview focuses on her experiences in the New York City school system, her experiences working in the Gay Liberation Front and co-founding the Radicalesbians, her work as a photographer and chronicler of the gay liberation movement, and her work as a social worker and psychotherapist. Shumsky's story details the origins of lesbian feminism from an intimate perspective, those policing this movement, internal discord, and commune life. She also illustrates the experience of being a lesbian psychotherapist, and how her identification as a lesbian changes her relationships with her patients and the larger discipline.
    Shumsky, Ellen
    - Video interview of Ellen Shumsky
    - Transcript of interview of Ellen Shumsky (Box 3)
  - Laura Sullivan interviewed by Melissa Yvette Pena, 2011 April 7; Sullivan, Laura; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Laura Sullivan (a.k.a. "M.L.") (b. August 1, 1959) grew up in Westport, CT. The third of five children from a middle-class Italian-American family, she was raised as a Roman Catholic and attended Catholic schools throughout her primary and secondary school education, until she attended Yale University in the late 1970s. After graduation, she became a physical therapist at Yale New Haven Hospital, where she worked for eighteen years, during which time she married and had a daughter. In the early 1990s, after becoming disillusioned with her role as a physical therapist, she and her business partner, Samantha, opened the Chateau, the first women-owned and operated BDSM club in Connecticut. A strong advocate for BDSM awareness, the Chateau was a safe space for employees and patrons to find community and "play." M.L. left the Chateau in the mid-1990s over creative differences wither her business partner, and divorced her husband in the early 1990s, suffering through a tumultuous child custody battle, where her BDSM interests and activities were major factors in the court proceedings. She now lives with her daughter and leather family in Connecticut, where they run a small, private BDSM club.